– – – –
– – – – – – – – – – – – – – – – – –
– – – – – – – – – – – – – – – – – – – – –
– – – – – – – – – – – – – – – –
– – – – – – – – – – – – – – – – – – – – I
don't mean privacy. I mean it's private to
Amazon. They own it. We call these
administrative identity systems because
they're designed to administer identity
for a specific purpose in a specific
domain. In this case, it's Amazon, but you
know, there are millions of them. The
system, the identifiers, how they work are
owned and controlled by Amazon. They're
the subject of Amazon's terms and
conditions. They're useful for
establishing trust within a domain, but
they're not useful for establishing trust
across domains. People are party to
dozens, hundreds, thousands of these
things. I have over a thousand entries in
my one password.
In contrast, decentralized identity flips
that model. The person becomes the center
of trust and credentials about that trust
flow through protocols rather than
platforms. Unlike the decentralized
identity model, decentralized identity
provides a consistent experience for
interacting with all of the relationships
in your digital life. But decentralization
alone isn't enough. What we really need is
what I think is called first-person
identity, a way for people to act as
themselves online, not as managed account.
I like the term first person identity
better than decentralized because it's
more clearly distinguishes that identity
is based on the individual, the first
party in a relationship. First person
describes an idea that most people
understand naturally. We're taught about
we're taught this in grade school. First
person is I, me, myself, mine. First
person describes precisely the kind of
thinking that will allow people to create
their own online relationships without an
intermediating administrator like a social
network. In first-person identity, you
might have relationships and credentials
from your employer, from your bank, from
your school, from the driver's license
bureau, and so on. You can use these alone
or in combination to prove things about
yourself. In first-person identity, people
are the integration point for information
about themselves. ourselves. Now, why does
this matter so much? It matters because
something essential is missing in our
digital lives. Maybe.
There we go. The real challenge online
isn't utility or convenience. its
proximity. In the physical world, we're
next to each other. We rely on tacit
knowledge that we gain from our senses to
see when we see and speak with people. We
use this tacit information to establish
trust. We don't have that online. Online,
we interact at a distance through screens
and systems and platforms that usually are
not controlled by us. Our relationships
are mediated by companies rather than
being direct. Let's talk about what that
distance costs us and how endorsement
rather than control can close it.
Descartes didn't say, I have a Google
login, therefore I am. He said, I think,
therefore I am. We exist independent of
anything else around us. Now, that's where
endorsement comes in. It bridges the gap
of distance. It allows people or anything
half a world away to trust who you are
because your own state endorses what
you're saying, your assertions that you're
making. SEDI, State Endorsed Digital
Identity, doesn't give you an identity.
You already have one. Rather, SEDI
endorses it. It provides the assurance we
need to act confidently across digital
distances. So the problem isn't that we
lack digital IDs. We've got plenty of
those. I've got a thousand. It's that we
lack standing in the online world. We are
ghosts existing only through the grace of
some company. We are not embodied
autonomous agents. SEDI changes that.
Again, it doesn't create your identity. It
endorses it and gives you the ability to
act across distance that can lead to
something much bigger. A chance to reclaim
our digital freedom. First-person identity
represents a chance for us to declare our
independence in the digital realm. to
regain the freedom to act as ourselves.
SEDI enables that by supporting the
individual and giving each of us a place
to stand online. Freedom in a digital
world begins when we act from our own
identity, not one assigned to us and
mediated by someone else. This is our
moment to build a digital world that
honors human dignity. A world where we are
free to live and act as ourselves, as
digital citizens rather than digital
subjects. If we don't build it, someone
else will. And it will reflect their
goals, goals that probably don't align
with the ones we think they should have.
For Utah, this is a chance to lead by
example, demonstrating that trust in
identity can scale without surveillance.
Across the US, SEDI can mark a shift from
digital subjects to digital citizens,
people who live effective online lives
with agency and respect. We have the
opportunity to build a digital world that
respects human dignity, a world where
people are free to live and act for
themselves. Let's not squander that
opportunity. community.